Guide to the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom. Chapel Hill Branch (N.C.) Records, 1939-2005 and undated RL.01395
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Women's International League for Peace and Freedom. Chapel Hill Branch (N.C.) records
1939-2005 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Women's International League for Peace and Freedom
RL.01395
8 Linear Feet
Branch of an international peace advocacy organization founded in 1915; formerly known as the Chapel Hill Branch (N.C.). Contains meeting agendas and minutes, directories, conference reports, group organizing information, correspondence including some with Senators Jesse Helms,John Edwards and David Price, Peace and Freedom, the magazine of the WILPF, legislative bulletins, clippings, an oral history interview with founding member Charlotte Adams, song lyrics, newsletters, videos, photographs, and other material documenting their efforts. A few of the newsletters document the activities of the Triangle Branch of WILPF. The collection also includes information files on activism for nuclear arms control, nuclear disarmament, and bans on nuclear testing that continue to document WILPF's activities to promote world peace. Also includes correspondence among WILPF members; meeting agendas and minutes for both WILFP and the Orange County North Carolina Peace Coalition; national petitions against nuclear weapons; and issues of Peace and Freedom, and the branch's newsletter. The collection also includes comprises newsletters, clippings, committee minutes, fundraising files, publicity materials for WILPF events and other groups' events, and incoming and outgoing correspondence with politicians and groups similar to the WILPF. Also includes videocassette tapes, photographs, and scrapbooks and a journal compiled by Charlotte Adams and documenting earlier years of the organization (1938-1964). Some of the audiovisual materials have use copies, but others do not; please speak to a reference archivist before use. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
6000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Women's International League for Peace and Freedom. Chapel Hill Branch (N.C.) Records, 1939-2005 were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1999-2004.
Biographical Note
The Women's International League for Peace and Freedom. Chapel Hill Branch (N.C.) is a branch of an international peace advocacy organization founded in 1915.
Collection Overview
Contains meeting agendas and minutes, directories, conference reports, group organizing information, correspondence including some with Senators Jesse Helms,John Edwards and David Price, Peace and Freedom, the magazine of the WILPF, legislative bulletins, clippings, an oral history interview with founding member Charlotte Adams, song lyrics, newsletters, videos, photographs, and other material documenting their efforts. A few of the newsletters document the activities of the Triangle Branch of WILPF. The collection also includes information files on activism for nuclear arms control, nuclear disarmament, and bans on nuclear testing that continue to document WILPF's activities to promote world peace. Also includes correspondence among WILPF members; meeting agendas and minutes for both WILFP and the Orange County North Carolina Peace Coalition; national petitions against nuclear weapons; and issues of Peace and Freedom, and the branch's newsletter. The collection also includes comprises newsletters, clippings, committee minutes, fundraising files, publicity materials for WILPF events and other groups' events, and incoming and outgoing correspondence with politicians and groups similar to the WILPF. Also includes videocassette tapes, photographs, and scrapbooks and a journal compiled by Charlotte Adams and documenting earlier years of the organization (1938-1964). Some of the audiovisual materials have use copies, but others do not; please speak to a reference archivist before use. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
DVDs; Color photographs; Videocassettes; Chapel Hill (N.C.) -- History; Women -- Societies and clubs; Peace movements -- United States -- 20th century; Nuclear nonproliferation; Nuclear disarmament; Nuclear arms control; Antinuclear movement; Community organization -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Newsletters; Helms, Jesse; Women's International League for Peace and Freedom; Women's International League for Peace and Freedom
- Administrative Files, 1939-1942 and undated, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains materials that document the operations of the Chapel Hill office.
  Arrangement note
  Files are arranged in lose chronological order, and includes administrative files from the U.S. secion and international section of WILPF.
  - 1939-1942 and undated (Box 1)
  - 1951-1975 (Box 1)
  - 1950s-1970s (Box 1)
  - 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - 1980-1998 (Box 1)
  - 1999-2005 (Box 1)
  - Notes, Correspondence, and Treasurer's Reports, 2000-2004 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1999 (Box 2)
  - WILPF Organizing How-tos, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Publicity, 1999-2002; Program Work, 1994-2003; Correspondence with Congress, 1999-2002 (Box 2)
  - Clippings of WILPF Members, 1997-2003 (Box 2)
  - U.S. WILPF, 1967-2004 and undated(3 folders) (Box 2)
  - International WILPF, 1971-1980 and undated (Box 2)
- Subject Files, 1961-2003 and undated, 5 boxes
  Contains articles, programs, clippings, correspondence and reports pertaining to nuclear disarmament, anti-war protests, and the activities of WILPF.
  Files are arranged in alphabetical order, and in chronological order within that.
  - Admiral Carroll, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Afghanistan, 2001-2002 (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Bush Administration, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Cassini Space Probe, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Charlotte Adams, 1975-2001 (Box 3)
  - Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty, 1998-2000 (Box 3)
  - Criticisms of WILPF, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Cuba, 2001 (Box 3)
  - De-Alerting, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Foreign Policy in the Age of Nuclear Weapons, 2000 (Box 3)
  - FCC, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Gulf War, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Health Care, 2002-2003 (Box 3)
  - International Women's Year, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Iraq, 1998-2003 (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Iraq, 1998-2003 (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Kosovo and Yugoslavia, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Landmines, 1997 (Box 4)
  - LEAP-Peace Action Demographics Project, 2000-2001 (Box 4)
  - Mount Olive Boycotts, 2001 (Box 4)
  - NC Warn, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Nuclear Disarmament, 1961-2003 and undated (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Nuclear Disarmament, 1961-2003 and undated(10 folders) (Box 5)
  - Nuclear Disarmament, 1961-2003 and undated (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty, 1997-2000 and undated (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Panama, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Peace in the Middle East, 2001-2003 (Box 6)
  - Orange County Peace Coalition, 1998-2001 (Box 6)
  - Transnational Foundation for Peace and Future Research, 1999-2001 (Box 6)
  - US Army School of the Americas, 1994 (Box 6)
  - Vietnam War, 1972-1973 and undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1997-2003 and undated (Box 7)
- Printed Materials,1955-1999 and undated, 1 box
  Material relating to the activities of WILPF as well as other anti-war organizations
  Files are arranged in chronological order.
  - 1955-1985 and undated (Box 7)
  - 1967-1973 and undated (Box 7)
  - 1972-1999 and undated (Box 7)
  - 1980-2000 and undated (Box 7)
  - 1983-1988 and undated (Box 7)
  - 1993-1996 and undated (Box 7)
  - 1997-1999 and undated (Box 7)
  - 1998-1999 and undated (Box 7)
- Publications 1971-2002, 1 box
  Contains Pax et Libertas, a publication of the International section of WILPF, as well as Peace and Freedom, the U.S. section of WILPF
  Items are arranged chronologically.
  - Pax et Libertas,1971-1973 (Box 8)
  - Peace and Freedom, 1974-2002 (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Peace and Freedom, 1971-1973 (Box 9)
- Photos 1975-2003 and undated, 1 box
  Photos from WILPF-sponsored events.
  Items are arranged in alphabetical order
  - Admiral Carroll Visit to UNC, 2000 (Box 8)
  - Album-"The Encampment", undated (Box 8)
  - Charlotte Adams and Sadie Hughley, undated (Box 8)
  - Events and Charlotte Adams, 2002 and undated (Box 8)
  - Events, 2003 and undated (Box 8)
  - First International Women's Year Meeting, 1975 (Box 8)
  - July 4 Celebration in Carrboro, N.C., 1997 (Box 8)
  - Regional WILPF Meeting, September 1986 (Box 8)
- Audiovisual Materials 1987-1999 and undated, 1 box
  Includes educational videos on nuclear disarmament, as well as audio recordings of WILPF events, including an interview with Charlotte Adams.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
  - Audiovisual materials (Box 10)
- Scrapbooks 1950s-1992 and undated, 3 boxes
  - 1967-1970 and undated (Box 10)
  - 1950s-1980s (Box 11)
  - 1970-1992 (Box 12)